<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="194229">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1880-12-13">13.12.1880</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">16.6.1880 &#x2013; 30.4.1881</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>13.12.1880 Montag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName> Dec 13 Monday</p>
            <p>Today is the distribution of Prizez At 3 o&#x2019;clock <persName key="581">Aunt
               Rose</persName> and <persName key="856">aunt
               Lulu</persName> arrive At <hi rend="ul">2</hi> ½ there is a great scuffle inthe passages; we
               have been told to go down into the library we all take our seats and presently the
               ladys and gentlemen take their seats. The head<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="667">Sneyd-Kynnersley</persName>
               </note> gets up and makes a short report of the third set and 4<hi rend="ul.2">
                  <hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> division. <persName key="667">The head</persName> sits down and says &#x201e;I leave
               the other reports to <persName key="857">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Macdonald</persName>, upon which <persName key="857">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Macdonald</persName> gets up and gives the following report<note type="com">Hier war ein beidseitig bedrucktes Blatt eingeklebt, das wohl einem
                     yearbook o. ä. der Schule entnommen und mit "Kessler" unterzeichnet ist. Jetzt ist
                     das Blatt lose in die Seiten des Tagebuches gelegt. Breite: 11,1 cm, Länge: 18,1
                     cm. Der Text lautet wie folgt (Nicht alle Formatierungen wurden
                     übernommen):</note>
            </p>
           
            <p>
               <orgName key="69740">St. George School</orgName>, <placeName key="49097">Ascot</placeName>
            </p>
            <p> TRIALS, CHRISTMAS, 1880.</p>
            <p>---</p>
            <p>Report of the Examiner, <persName key="857">Rev. F. W. Macdonald</persName>, M. A,
               Queen&#x2019;s College, Oxon.</p>
            <p>After I had set the papers for these trials, I felt afraid that they would be too
               hard for the boys, but as soon as I began to look over the answers, I found that,
               though the standard was much higher than that of last trials, the boys were generally
               up to it. I have been much struck with the great neatness displayed throughout, and
               the even character of the work in the school, which shews that in this school the
               dull boy is not sacrificed to the clever one as is so often the case, but all pains
               are taken with each individual.</p>
            <p>In &#x201e;Arithmetic,&#x201c; the work is very good and above the average, the Practice sums being
               particularly well done, while the Proportion and Algebra are rather weak: <persName key="4855">Fry</persName>, <persName key="693">Tomlin</persName>, and <persName key="916">Jay</persName> are deserving of great praise, while I notice the
               accuracy of <persName key="1020">Waterhouse</persName>, and the reverse with respect
               to <persName key="895">Hall, ma.</persName> and <persName key="893">Heysham</persName>.</p>
            <p>In the &#x201e;French&#x201c; which is generally good, <persName key="4855">Fry</persName>,
                  <persName key="885">Ferguson</persName>, and <persName key="910">Bowring,
                  mi</persName>, are preeminent.</p>
            <p>The Scripture astonished me; it was excellent throughout, but <persName key="4855">Fry</persName> and <persName key="693">Tomlin</persName>, who both got full
               marks, <persName key="894">Olliver</persName>, <persName key="1113">Whittaker</persName>, <persName key="728">Bell</persName>, <persName key="547">Palk</persName>, <persName key="703">Scott</persName> and Kessler, are particularly deserving of praise; Bald must pay more
               attention to this subject.</p>
            <p>The &#x201e;History and Geography&#x201c; were well done, <persName key="4855">Fry</persName>,
                  <persName key="695">Mackenzie</persName>, and Kessler shewing most proficiency.</p>
            <p>The &#x201e;English&#x201c; paper was answered as well as I expected, and I should imagine that
               essay writing was practised a good deal, as nearly every boy gave me his opinion as
               to the advantages and the reverse of either <hi rend="i">Old age</hi>, <hi rend="i">Peace</hi>, or <hi rend="i">Pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Classical subjects, the &#x201e;Grammar&#x201c; in all divisions was good: the papers were
               difficult, but still in Division I. there was no boy who did not obtain half marks,
               while <persName key="4855">Fry</persName>, <persName key="893">Heysham</persName>,
               and <persName key="885">Ferguson</persName> were within 100 of full marks: in
               Division II., <persName key="695">Mackenzie</persName> and <persName key="726">Bowring, ma</persName>, were preeminent, but <persName key="675">Thomson,
                  mi.</persName>, and <persName key="80771">Hall, mi.</persName>, some way behind
               the rest.</p>
            <p>In Division III. the <hi rend="i">Latin Grammar</hi> was particularly good; Bald
               heads the list, and <persName key="689">Trelawny</persName> who is worst, has
               obtained nearly half marks.</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">Latin Prose</hi>, there is little fault to find, but Division I. must
               be careful about the use of the Subjunctive: <persName key="4855">Fry</persName> and
                  <persName key="885">Ferguson</persName>, did excellent papers.</p>
            <p>In Division II. <persName key="762">Powell</persName> and <persName key="728">Bell</persName> shewed that they had taken great pains, while <persName key="916">Jay</persName> and <persName key="763">Schuster</persName> lost marks through
               carelessness, and <persName key="80771">Hall, mi.</persName> and <persName key="884">Watson</persName> evidently consider Latin Prose beneath their attention.</p>
            <p>In Division III. Kessler is far above the rest. </p>
            <p>In the <hi rend="i">Translations</hi>, Division I. all did well except <persName key="895">Hall, ma.</persName>, who I fancy lacked perseverance; in Greek
               Translation they were weak, but this is accounted for by the fact that they have not
               attempted idiomatic Greek.</p>
            <p>Division II. <persName key="728">Bell</persName> did well, but <persName key="884">Watson</persName>, <persName key="80771">Hall, mi.</persName>, and <persName key="675">Thomson, mi.</persName> were weak. The papers of this division on this
               subject, shew that they are well grounded and carefully taught.</p>
            <p>Division III. had too difficult a paper, but Kessler
               and <persName key="912">Blundell</persName> did so well that they led me to think
               that some of the others might have done better; this division evidently knew more
               than they could express on paper.</p>
            <p>In Latin Verses, the standard is not high, Division II. did better than those above
               them.</p>
            <p>To sum up, the work appears to be thorough - there is great uniformity. Where all
               branches of education are attended to equally, it is difficult to mention any one
               point in which the boys particularly excel, but, if anything, I am inclined to think
               that the French has been the most satisfactory work in an examination which has been
               decidedly above the average of attainments amongst boys of this age.</p>
            <p>(Signed), <persName key="857">F. W. MACDONALD</persName>, M.A., <placeName key="49586">Oxon</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Vicar of <placeName key="80772">Stapleford</placeName> and <placeName key="80773">Berwick</placeName>, Wilts.<note type="com">Ende der Abschrift. Sie ist mit dem
                  Prägestempel von Kessler versehen und mit &#x201e;Kessler&#x201c; unterschrieben. Ein weiteres Blatt ist eingelegt: Ein Zeitungsausschnitt &#x201e;<name type="work" key="81261">Moderne Pariser Soiréen</name>&#x201c; von <persName key="18037">Kaufmann</persName>; Breite: 29 cm, Länge 17,6 cm, der Artikel wird auf der
                  Rückseite fortgeführt. Keine Abschrift.</note>
            </p>
            <p> After this <persName key="857">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Macdonald</persName> sat down again and <persName key="667">the
                  head</persName> gets up and says <lb/>&#x201e;Now I will proceed with the prizes&#x201c;
                  &#x201e;<persName key="4855">Fry</persName> first division Prize.&#x201c; <persName key="4855">Fry</persName> walks up amidst thunders of applause.</p>
            <p>&#x201e;<persName key="728">Bell</persName> second division Prize,&#x201c; more applause After some
               time he says &#x201e;Kessler french prize&#x201c; I go up trembling after some time he again calls
               my name for Geography this time there is a good deal of applauds soon the prizegiving
               is finished</p>
            <p>We all go upstairs and at 3 ½ the concert begins. We all that sing have to sit on the
               staircase. <persName key="581">Aunt
                  Rose</persName> and <persName key="856">aunt
                  Lulu</persName> go away before the end of the first part. The concert lasts 3
               hours: from 3½ to 6½. Then we have tea to which we have turkey and buns but in the
               evening after chapel I am very sick.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>