<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="274526">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1881-08-01">1.8.1881</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">1.5.1881 &#x2013; 9.11.1881</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1.8.1881 Montag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName> August 1<hi rend="ul.2">
                  <hi rend="sup">rst</hi>
               </hi> 1881 Monday</p>
            <p>The prizes were given today few people came and those who did come were almost
                    all from the neighbourhood. I got an extra Scripture prize for only being 3
                    marks of <persName key="894">Oliver</persName> who got the first Scripture
                    prize. I also got a French prize. <persName key="913">Thomson ma.</persName> got
                        1<hi rend="ul.2">
                  <hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               </hi> div total work prize very fine <persName key="8407">Shakespeare</persName>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note type="com">Hier ist wieder der Bericht des Examinators eingeklebt. Es
                        folgt die Abschrift. Formatierungen wurden nicht alle übernommen. Auf dem
                        Blatt steht in Kesslers Hand: &#x201e;Report read by <persName key="857">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                        <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                     </hi> Macdonald</persName> at the
                        prizes&#x201c;.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <orgName key="69740">S. George&#x2019;s School</orgName>, <placeName key="49097">Ascot</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>--- TRIALS, JULY, 1881. --- </p>
            <p>Report of the Examiner, Rev. <persName key="857">F. W. Macdonald</persName>,
                    M.A., <orgName key="70036">Queen&#x2019;s College</orgName>, <placeName key="49586">Oxford</placeName>. </p>
            <p> On this my second Examination of this School, I am glad to find that the
                    Standard of Work has in no respect deteriorated, while improvement has been made
                    in those subjects which I considered last Trials to be weaker than the rest. </p>
            <p>I have again been impressed with the level character of the work, and the great
                    neatness with which the papers have been answered.</p>
            <p>With regard to English: &#x2013; in the Scripture which was a difficult paper. <persName key="894">Olliver</persName>, Count Kessler,
                        <persName key="778">Lord Uffington</persName>, and <persName key="547">Palk</persName> were particularly good, <persName key="681">Bald</persName>, on the other hand has not improved in this respect. In History
                    and Geography, <persName key="913">Thomson, ma.</persName>, <persName key="675">Thomson, mi.</persName>, and <persName key="679">Sellon</persName> deserve high
                    praise; dates however must be in the future more carefully got up. I was also
                    struck with the improvement in Essay Writing particularly noticeable in
                    Divisions 2 and 4. </p>
            <p>In Classical Work, Division I. show a distinct improvement in Greek Translation
                    and Greek Grammar, <persName key="913">Thomson, ma.</persName> in the latter
                    gaining within 7 of the full marks: the Prepositions are the weak point in this
                    subject.</p>
            <p>In Latin Grammar, <persName key="913">Thomson, ma.</persName> again distinguishes
                    himself, closely followed by <persName key="693">Tomlin</persName>, whose
                    general neatness in paper work is to be specially commended. </p>
            <p>The Latin Translation was fairly done by all. <persName key="1020">Waterhouse&#x2019;s</persName> paper showing that he had taken great pains. </p>
            <p>The Latin Composition was really well done throughout. <persName key="894">Olliver</persName> being preeminent.</p>
            <p>The Unseen Translation was perhaps a little too easy; it was mastered by all the
                    boys. </p>
            <p>In Greek Composition, the papers were better than I expected. Thomson<note type="com">Unklar welcher, <persName key="913">Thomson, ma.</persName> oder <persName key="675">Thomson, mi.</persName>
               </note>, <persName key="894">Olliver</persName> and <persName key="1020">Waterhouse</persName> pleased me much by their accuracy in the
                    Grammar. </p>
            <p>The Latin Verses throughout the School were better than those of last Trials, but
                    there is still great room for improvement, and Division III. must pay more
                    attention to Prosody rules.</p>
            <p>Division II. did well in Latin Translation, notably Count
                        Kessler, but I was more struck by the excellent way in which this
                    Division managed their Greek Translation, a subject difficult to beginners.</p>
            <p> In Latin Prose, more attention must be paid to the use of Prepositions. The
                    Latin Grammar is very much improved. The Greek Grammar paper was accurately
                    done, though weakness was shown in the declension of nouns, <persName key="681">Bald</persName> and <persName key="703">Scott</persName> are here some way
                    behind the rest. In this Division <persName key="916">Jay</persName>, <persName key="763">Schuster</persName> and Count
                        Kessler show great promise.</p>
            <p>In Division III. the best work was done in the Latin Grammar Paper, which was
                    remarkably well answered throughout, particularly by
                    <persName key="679">Sellon</persName>.</p>
            <p>In the Greek Grammar, more attention must be paid to the Comparison of
                    Adjectives. <persName key="547">Palk</persName> distinguished himself in this
                    paper.</p>
            <p>The Latin Prose was poor. In the Latin Translation, the Unseen Passages were
                    rather too difficult. </p>
            <p>In Mathematics and French, the standard of the work is high, above the average.
                    In the former subject <persName key="1113">Whittaker</persName> and <persName key="764">Wormald</persName> in their respective Sets did excellent papers,
                    while <persName key="80902">Speer, ma.</persName>., and <persName key="1112">Mortimer, ma.</persName> must pay more attention. <persName key="693">Tomlin</persName> must be commended for his Euclid and Algebra.</p>
            <p>In French, <persName key="1020">Waterhouse</persName> (Set.1) and Count Kessler and <persName key="80903">Pilcher</persName> (Set 2) deserve great praise.</p>
            <p> I cannot speak too highly of these two departments, so important in these days
                    of Modern Education.</p>
            <p>On the whole I, consider this Examination to have evinced almost greater evenness
                    as to the work than last Trials, there being no real failures; this is a great
                    desideratum in a School of this size, and a sign of the pains taken with each
                    individual boy.</p>
            <p>(Signed)</p>
            <p>
               <persName key="857">F. W. MACDONALD</persName>, M.A., Oxon, Vicar of <placeName key="80772">Stapleford</placeName> and <placeName key="80773">Berwick</placeName>, Wilts.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>