<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="150912">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49411">Blankenburg</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1884-06-07">7.6.1884</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>7.6.1884 Samstag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49411">Blankenburg</placeName>. June 7. 1884.</p>
            <p>This morning I was woke at half past three to see the sun rise and did not like it
               all. It was not worth ones while to get up so early to see so little. I went to bed
               again then and got up again at 8 o&#x2019;clock had breakfast and packed my things. When all
               was ready I went down into the garden and looked through the telescope. When
                  <persName key="856">aunt Lulu</persName> came down we went up to the Bülow&#x2019;s Höhe
               and from there to the Rosstrappe where we made the man shoot so that we might hear
               the echo and gave him 30 pf. for it. We then walked down the Schurre into the
               Bodethal, and from there walked on to the Teufelsbrücke. On both sides high rocks
               fall almost straight into the Bode which rushes on through the Kessel foaming and
               raging. On the other side of the Teufelsbrücke we walked on a little way and then
               turned and walked to the <orgName key="66858">Waldkater</orgName> by the Königsruhe
               and the Jungfernbrücke. From the <orgName key="66858">Waldkater</orgName> I walked up
               the Hexentreppe, 1120 high steps some of them loose, some high and some low, to the
               Hexentanzplatz. <persName key="856">Aunt Lulu</persName> drove up. At the top I had a
               glass of milk and spent the time till the carriage came in walking to the
               Riesenschloss and looking at the scenery. We then drove down to <orgName key="66859">Hotel Zehpfund</orgName> in <placeName key="49410">Thale</placeName> and had
               dinner there looked at the shops and bought some things and went to the <orgName key="66858">Waldkater</orgName> where we had coffee. At half past four we drove
               away from <placeName key="49410">Thale</placeName> to the Regenstein near here which
               is very interesting. There is a ruin of a castle on it which was besieged and taken
               by <persName key="8321">Frederick the great</persName> by his bombarding the well and
               smashing it up so that the French who where in it could get no more water in 1756. We
               also saw the <unclear instant="false">outhöhle</unclear> in one of which a <persName key="1360">princess of Heimburg</persName> was shut up but bored her way through the
               thinnest part of the wall with her ring! Most of the remaining rooms are hewn out of
               the rock and there is still a tower in it built by <persName key="1363">Henry I the
                  Birdcatcher</persName> in the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. The Romans were
               here too, and in olden times it was a Raubburg one of the counts let himself out of a
               window was taken and put into a wooden box. From the Regenstein we drove to
                  <placeName key="49411">Blankenburg</placeName> to the <orgName key="66860">Weisse
                  Adler</orgName> where we have two very nice large rooms. In the evening we went to
               the Thie and heard the band. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>