<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="194564">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName key="49396" type="write">Wernigerode</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1884-06-06">6.6.1884</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>6.6.1884 Freitag</head>
            <p>
               <orgName key="66857">Rosstrappe Hotel</orgName>
               <note type="reg">
                  <placeName key="49396" type="write">Wernigerode</placeName>
               </note>. June 6. 1884.</p>
            <p>Walked up the Lindenberg this morning in <placeName key="49396">Wernigerode</placeName>, from where there is a very fine view on to the castle
               and town. We then went down the Burgstrasse where I bought a very nice little stick
               for 90 pf. We had already ordered our carriage, so when we came home after having
               breakfasted we drove away to Rübeland. The road went through <placeName key="49404">Eltingerode</placeName>, where we saw the <placeName key="66855">Blaue
                  Engel</placeName> in which <persName key="856">aunt Lulu</persName> was almost
               eaten up by fleas last time she was here. From there we drove to the hotel <placeName key="66856">Grüne Tanne</placeName> in 30 minutes. From the <orgName key="66856">Grüne Tanne</orgName> we had to go up a rather steep hill to the Bauman&#x2019;s Höhle a
               large grotto but not so large as Remouchamps. We walked in a kind of procession. The
               guide first the <persName key="856">aunt Lulu</persName> and last a young couple in
               their honeymoon They did nothing but call each other &#x201e;Liebchen&#x201c; and &#x201e;Mäuschen&#x201c; and
               &#x201e;Engel&#x201c; etc. Each of us men had a lamp; the guide also lit some limelight in some
               places. From Rübeland we drove on to <placeName key="49406">Treseburg</placeName>.
               The way down to <placeName key="49406">Treseburg</placeName> is one of the most
               beautiful in the Harz. On both sides are high mountains covered with firtrees etc.
               which look like feathers in the distance, and down in the valley the Bode rushes
               through. On the way to <placeName key="49406">Treseburg</placeName> we went up to the
               Wilhelmsblick from which one can see the Bode for a long way. Down at <placeName key="49406">Treseburg</placeName> we had some very good sour milk at the <orgName key="66854">Weisse Hirsch</orgName>. From <placeName key="49406">Treseburg</placeName> we drove uphill to the Rosstrappe where we are staying this
               night. From the Hotel we directly walked on to the Rosstrappe with the horseshoe.
               From the Rassmannshöhe we had a beautiful view into the Bodethal on to the Teufels
               Brücke. The scenery was wild and grand beyond description. The Hexentanzplatz we
               could also see. From my window here I have got a very far view: <placeName key="49408">Halberstadt</placeName>, <placeName key="49409">Quedlinburg</placeName>, <placeName key="49410">Thale</placeName> etc and the
               hills in the distance, the whole now lit by the moon, and the thousand little lights
               of the towns and villages are very picturesque. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>