<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="150494">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1881-11-12">12.11.1881</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>12.11.1881 Samstag</head>
            
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName> . 12. November. 1881.
               Saturday.</p>
            <p>This morning we started for the choir expedition. We went down to <placeName key="49050">London</placeName> by the 8.45 train and got there about 9. We
               directly took 2 busses and drove to the Houses of Parliament but finding that they
               were not yet open we went in to <placeName key="56690">Westminster Abbey</placeName>
               where we heard the beginning of the morning service. Then we went back to the houses
               of Parliament and were let in by the Victoria tower. The rooms were splendid,
               decorated with frescos, gilding, woodcarving and other ornaments. We first came to
               the queens<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="9544">Victoria I.</persName>
               </note> robing room in which there is a very fine throne. We then went through
               various smaller rooms and at last came to the where we saw another very fine throne.
               All the seats are covered with red leather. then we were taken through various
               passages decorated with beautiful frescoes to the house of Commons which looks very
               mean after the house of Lords. We there saw the bar by which <persName key="1036">Bradlaugh</persName> had been stopped the last time he tried to enter the house
               by force. Then we went into a law court where <persName key="1037">Lord
                  Coleridge</persName> was sitting. <persName key="1036">Bradlaugh</persName> was
               also there. He looked very fat and mean and altogether disgusting. We afterwards went
               into some more law courts and into the court of exchequers where rather an amusing
               case. about forgeing a signature, was going on. Westminster hall struck me as being a
               very fine place. We afterwards went down the Thames to London-bridge in the same boat
               as <persName key="5696">Gladstone</persName>. We then saw a chrysanthemum show said
               to be the finest in the world; some of the chrysanthemum were very pretty. We also
               bought some tortoises and other reptiles at Greens in <placeName key="59635">Covent Garden</placeName>. We had a very good dinner a 2/ a head at
                  <orgName key="66955">the Horse Shoe hotel</orgName>. Then we walked to the
                  <orgName key="66956">Prince of Wales&#x2019; theatre</orgName> and saw the &#x201e;<name type="work" key="28485">Colonel</name>&#x201c;<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="18864">Burnand</persName>
               </note> which takes the aesthetes off beautifully. After the <name type="work" key="28485">Colonel</name> we went to <orgName key="66957">Madame
                  Tussauds</orgName> and saw the wax works. I was quite taken in by a wax policeman.
               We then drove for to a chemists where we ordered some Sodium and some potash for
               experiments; then we drove to Waterloo station and took the train to <placeName key="49097">Ascot</placeName> where we arrived at about 10.30. Those of the choir
               who are in the first div. (I included) went down to the terrapyn pool house and put
               the animals we had bought at <persName>Green&#x2019;s</persName> into and round about it and
               afterwards had some &#x201e;negus&#x201c; and went to bed. We posted a letter, to <persName key="695">Mackenzie</persName>, signed Eliza Wicks<note type="com">Von den
                  Schülern erfundene Person.</note> who is supposed to be an old friend of his
               mothers. He firmly believes in her. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>