<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="148873">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49289">Rigi</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1885-08-11">11.8.1885</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>11.8.1885 Dienstag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49289">Rigi</placeName>
               <orgName key="49369">Kaltbad</orgName>. August 11. 1885. Tuesday.</p>
            <p>Again worked in the same place in the morning. In the afternoon read the papers and
               walked up to Staffelhöhe with <persName key="103">Mamma</persName> and <persName key="104">Baby</persName>. As it began to lighten and thunder we walked back very
               soon though and I wrote and read in <persName key="103">Mamma&#x2019;s</persName> room.
                  <persName key="103">Mamma</persName> read the last two chapters of <name type="work" key="28748">Mad. de Mineleko</name> to me, which she has shortly
               written. She is now working at <name type="work" key="28731">Wilma de Lashas</name>.
               which she began in April while <orgName key="67188">Lemerre</orgName> was reading
                  <name type="work" key="28586">Roland</name>. Danced in the evening. This morning
               at five the Steamwashapparatus began to go and woke everyone up. It sounds like a
               battery of cannons. Du reste we are not spared noise here. There was an individual on
               my landing who began grating his violin and producing the most heartwrending sound
               every morning before six. Thank goodness he is gone now. There is also a female who
               begins to thump the piano at five in the morning and pierces the temples and nerves
               of the house inmates with the most terrifying shrieks. In fact if one was to describe
               all the inhabitants of the <orgName key="49289">Kaltbad</orgName> one could get
               together a good lot of cures. There is that Roumanian with a craze on <persName key="1868">Sarah Bernhardt</persName>, with frizzly hair, a cadaverous looking
               face and wild eyes. À propos of her, the other day when her bathing woman did not dry
               her properly she went to her dressing table, pulled out a dagger and. told the
               terrified woman that if she did not dry her on the spot she would kill her. There is
                  <persName key="1869">old baron Oppenheim</persName> whose whig nearly flew away
               the other day and who always walks as if he had got the stomack ache, there is the
               &#x201e;femme au panache&#x201c; with the white feathers towering high above her, there is Mother
                  Goose<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="1867">Ricardo</persName>
               </note> with her rouge and cosmetics and yellow dresses and red and pink hats and
               juvenile look and 90 years, then <persName key="1870">old Ibrahim</persName> who is
               in love with <persName key="1872">prince George</persName> and last but not least
                  <persName key="1871">old Mariassi</persName> with her brown veil and dust cloak,
               who always sits with her back to the mountains: The charlatan is represented by
                  <persName key="1873">D<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Hermann</persName>. 4500 cases and 1663 deaths of the cholera in Spain
               yesterday. German demonstration before Zanzibar and <persName key="1319">General
                  Grant&#x2019;s</persName> funeral are the great topics now.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>