<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="194251">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich gesch체tzt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="K체rzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1881-12-19">19.12.1881</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>19.12.1881 Sonntag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49097">Ascot</placeName> December. 19.
                  1881</p>
            <p>Had a game of Prisoners base and Rounders in the morning. There was Reading over in
               the afternoon <persName key="176">Papa</persName> and aunt Rose<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="581">Lynch</persName>
               </note> came. I got the French Prize
                  &#x201e;<name type="work" key="28501">The Source of the Nile</name>&#x201c; by <persName key="1107">Speke</persName>. The following was the Report </p>
            <p>
               <note type="com">Hier ist der Bericht eingeklebt. Es folgt die Abschrift, wobei nicht alle Formatierungen 체bernommen wurden.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <orgName key="69740">S. George&#x2019;s School</orgName>, <placeName key="49097">Ascot</placeName>. </p>
            <p>--- </p>
            <p>TRIALS, CHRISTMAS, 1881.</p>
            <p>---</p>
            <p>Report of the Examiner, Rev. <persName key="857">F. W. Macdonald</persName>, M.A.,
                  <orgName key="80919">Queen&#x2019;s College</orgName>, <placeName key="49586">Oxford</placeName>. </p>
            <p>To begin with the English Subjects, the Scripture which required considerable
               thought, was fairly done throughout: In Div. I., <persName key="894">Olliver</persName>&#x2019;s paper was a long way the best. I was much pleased with the
               neatness and good writing of Div. II.</p>
            <p>The History was satisfactorily answered, but the knowledge of important dates is
               still weak. <persName key="912">Blundell</persName> must pay more attention to
               History. </p>
            <p>In Geography, Div. III. was weak.</p>
            <p>The Mathematical papers were not done quite as well as last time, there not being the
               same evenness in work: I think the maximum standard too high, and that it would be
               best to fix a lower standard for each set, and to work all the boys up to it; the
               elementary work was good: progress has been made in Euclid and Algebra.</p>
            <p>In French, Set I. did well, but unevenly, some boys being far ahead of others. To Set
               II. the same remark applies. The Grammar was excellent, but the Translation weak. The
               Pronunciation of those boys whom I examined viv창 voce is very good.</p>
            <p> With regard to Classical Subjects: - In Grammar, the papers were throughout the
               School well answered: Div. I. showed a marked advance in critical knowledge: Div. II
               failed to give the English of the different examples; their parsing was very good.
                  <persName key="894">Olliver</persName> in Div. I., <persName key="675">Thomson</persName> in Div. II., and <persName key="80920">Tottenham</persName> in
               Div. III., were particularly good in Greek Grammar. </p>
            <p>In Latin Translation, all Divisions did well. In Div. I., <persName key="695">Mackenzie</persName> must be more careful. In Div. II., <persName>Bowring</persName>, <persName key="675">Thomson</persName>, <persName key="884">Watson</persName>, and <persName>Hichens</persName>. made good attempts at
               Unseen. <persName key="547">Palk</persName> spoiled a capital paper by omitting this.
               In Div. III., <persName key="80903">Pilcher</persName> is to be particularly
               commended.</p>
            <p>In Greek Translation, Div. I. A. did satisfactorily; <persName key="695">Mackenzie</persName> showed great improvement and <persName key="1020">Waterhouse</persName> did a good paper. Div. II. have made progress.</p>
            <p>The Unseen Translation paper in Div. I., was done much better than last time.
                  <persName key="894">Olliver</persName>&#x2019;s paper was remarkably good.</p>
            <p>The Latin Verses were poor. Div. III. has has improved in Prosody rules.</p>
            <p>The Latin Prose, throughout all Divisions, shows marked improvement. <persName key="894">Olliver</persName>, in Div. I., did a capital piece, as did <persName key="675">Thomson</persName>, in Div. II., and <persName key="80903">Pilcher</persName>, in Div. III. More progress has been made in this subject than
               in any other.</p>
            <p>The Greek Prose of Div. I. quite came up to my expectations, and showed improvement,
               the competition being very close.</p>
            <p>I have been struck by the good work done throughout the examination by <persName key="894">Olliver</persName>, and with the progress made since last Trials by
                  <persName key="547">Palk</persName> and <persName key="911">Pearse</persName>.</p>
            <p>To sum up, there has been the same neatness and correct spelling displayed as on
               former occasions; the Standard has been as high, but the work, generally, has not
               been so level as at last Trials, when the evenness was particularly noticeable. It
               would be well not to raise the standard of work to suit any particular boys, but
               having fixed a maximum for the Term to work each individual boy up to it. The
               standard of work now, is quite high enough for boys of this age, and the Head and his
               Staff have reason to congratulate themselves on the result of their teaching,</p>
            <p>(Signed)</p>
            <p>
               <persName key="857">F. W. Macdonald</persName>, M.A., Oxon,</p>
            <p>Vicar of <placeName key="80772">Stapleford</placeName> and <placeName key="80773">Berwick</placeName>, Wilts. </p>
            <p>
               <note type="com">Zwischen den Seiten, nach dem letzten Eintrag, liegt eine Beilage: In
                  die Umschlagseiten eines Cahierheftes sind zwei Programme des Schulchores
                  eingeklebt. Vorne steht in Kesslers Hand: &#x201e;Memoires de Harry de Kessler&#x201c;. Auf die
                  Innenseite sind zwei Wappen eingeklebt. Das erste zeigt das Schulwappen, darunter
                  von Kessler: &#x201e;Arms of the school&#x201c;. Das zweite ein Piktogramm von einem Umschlag,
                  darunter: &#x201e;little fantaisie crest Mamma sends me on a letter&#x201c;.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>