<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="174963">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49069">Hamburg</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1885-05-20">20.5.1885</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>20.5.1885 Mittwoch</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49069">Hamburg</placeName> May 20.
      1885.</p>
            <p>
               <persName key="104">Gee</persName> has been very, very ill so that
      the doctors had almost given her up but according to a letter from
      <persName key="176">Papa</persName> to <persName key="856">aunt
      Lulu</persName> she is a little better and has again eaten a little milk and bread
      without vomiting it. It has again given me a little hope. I am almost well
      again, <persName key="176">Papas</persName> tongue is still bad
      <persName key="103">Mamma</persName> very exhausted. If only my darling
      <persName key="104">Gee</persName> could get better. Poor little thing she
      has such dreadful pain <persName key="103">Mamma</persName> writes, such
      terrific headaches, she lies away complaining. And she is already so exhausted
      by the measles. Poor little thing, what a cross she has to bear. The ice has
      constantly to be changed. I start every time the bell goes for fear of a
      telegramm or a letter with bad news. Whenever I see
      <persName key="856">aunt Lulu</persName> coming it frightens me for fear
      that something dreadful has happened. How thankful I shall be when, please God,
      my dear, dear little <persName key="104">sister</persName> really begins to
      get better again. I never till now thought one could expect a letter so
      longingly and yet with such trembling as I do. Everything that happens seems an
      omen for good or bad. This incertainty is really dreadful. I really tremble
      ever to be without a book or something to occupy me for fear of the dreadful,
      dreadful thoughts that arise. Oh how fervently I pray that all may end well;
      and yet I always feel a kind of oppressing, uncomfortable uncertain feeling,
      even when reading or working. Everything I read palls upon me and yet I cannot
      be without a book, I wish for company and when I have it I do not like to talk.
      Yet how small is my burden compared to that of poor
      <persName key="103">Mamma</persName> and <persName key="176">Papa</persName> and my poor, poor dear little
      <persName key="104">Gee</persName>. I do not wonder
      <persName key="103">Mamma</persName> can only keep up with Quinine. It is a
      regular relief to be able to put on paper, what one can tell nobody, write to
      noone.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>