<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="194836">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49084">Pyrmont</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1880-07-24">24.7.1880</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">16.6.1880 &#x2013; 30.4.1881</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>24.7.1880 Samstag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49084">Pyrmont</placeName> 24 July
      1880</p>
            <p>We went to the &#x201e;Dunsthöhle&#x201c; this
      morning It is a hole in the earth of the form of a 
      <graphic n="1" url="dia_hgk_18800724_or_01" width="5%" rend="inline"/> we went down to the bottom by a staircase, at the bottom
      the keeper opened a little gate and we again went down a
      few steps to the bottom of the pit here the keeper told us
      to stoop a little which we did; a strong smell of carbonic acide pervaded us
      and we were almost suffocated for the gas was then at a heighth of about 3 feet
      and any living thing or person who&#x2019;s respiratory organ is under that
      heighth would have been suffocated; in the time of the roulette lots of people
      used to come and lie down here to commit suicide. The
      keeper then took some straw lit it and plunged it in the gas at the very
      minute the flame went out and when he held it over the gas again it began to
      burn; the same thing happens to any human or living being that inhales this gas
      in the acid it faints and out of it it revives. The gas sometimes in less than
      five minutes mounts to the heighth of the second gate and higher so that one
      can not even get to this gate, it comes out of a cave which the man shewed us,
      this grotto is like the grotto of <placeName key="49090">Capri</placeName> in
      <placeName key="49089">Naples</placeName> with the only differences of being much
      smaller and there being no water here and there being some at
      <placeName key="49090">Capri</placeName> and the gas being non visible here and
      being visible at <placeName key="49089">Naples</placeName>. There are only two
      such places in the whole world here and at <placeName key="49089">Naples</placeName>. This pit here was discovered in 1724 by doctor
     Philippe Seife<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="74836">Seip, Johann</persName>
               </note> and an inscription relating the fact was put
      there in 1740. This afternoon the were races at one of which three running two
      were thrown. When the labourers raced one of them fell and broke his head at
      the donky race the boys all fought.<note type="com">Hier am Ende ist ein
        Stück Papier eingeklebt: ca. 1,5 cm breit und 3,7 cm lang. Es sieht aus,
        als sei das größte Stück davon abgerissen. Es steht darauf:
        "N. B. Fr or"</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>