<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="175809">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49096">Paris</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1881-05-01">1.5.1881</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">1.5.1881 &#x2013; 9.11.1881</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1.5.1881 Sonntag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49096">Paris</placeName>. 1. May. 1881. Sunday. S. rises
               4.33. sets 7.21.
            </p>
            <p>Full moon 13. <persName key="642">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Cook</persName> and <persName key="904">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Scudamore</persName> came to fetch me this morning for <placeName key="48884">Versaille<add hand="hgk">s</add>
               </placeName>. We started by the 10.30 train in which we could hardly get <add hand="hgk">a</add> places. When we got to <placeName key="48884">Versailles</placeName> we took the buss and drove to the <orgName key="67515">Museum</orgName>; but this not yet being open we strolled into the grounds. At
               twelve we went into the <orgName key="67515">Museum</orgName> where we saw the
               pictures of the admiral<add hand="hgk">s</add>, constables, Marshals and great
               warriors of France, pictures illustrating the history of France. <persName key="3939">Marie Antoinettes</persName> Private apartments and the &#x201e;salle des glaces&#x201c;, the
               hall in which the King of Prussia<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="10133">Wilhelm
                     I.</persName>
               </note> was crowned <persName key="10133">Emperor of Germany</persName>. We came out
               of the <orgName key="67515">Museum</orgName> a little past one and went to the little
               and the big Trianon where we saw the state carriages and the appartments occupied by
                  <persName key="5624">Madame de Maintenon</persName>, <persName key="3939">Marie
                  Antoinette</persName>, <persName key="8003">Napoleon 1<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">st</hi>
                  </hi>
               </persName>, <persName key="9589">Louis
                  Philippe</persName> and Queen Victoria<note type="reg">
                  <persName key="9544">Victoria I.</persName>
               </note>, and the
               hall in which <persName key="907">Bazaine</persName> was tried in 1873. After that we went to have breakfast at the
               <orgName key="81301">Hotel de France</orgName> on salmon, cutlets and potatoes and Coffee at
                  15.<hi rend="sup">fr.</hi>75. for three of us. Then we went to see the Band and
               &#x201e;Grandes-Eaux.&#x201c; We took seats at the basin de Neptune, at 4.25. and watched the
               swelling ant-like crowd, getting greater and greater roaring and rushing. Twice it
               started up on false alarm and sat down and twice that buzz grew and fell till at last
               the continual roar shewed the basin de Neptune was playing; we
               just looked at it and then walked sharply to the station where I took 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> class tickets. But once on the platform I saw the hard reality: the
               choice between stopping at <placeName key="48884">Versailles</placeName> or being
               buried with dust on the imperial: we chose the latter. At first we were very
               comfortable <hi rend="ul">but</hi> at <placeName key="48885">Ville
                  d&#x2019;Avray</placeName> A lot of of People got in and made it nearly impossible for
               other people to get in <hi rend="ul">but</hi> at <placeName key="48886">Suresne</placeName> ... O dear! the carriages in which there was one seat left
               were directly stormed by about 20 people, screaming and howling and swearing, and
               pushing and fighting and treading on corns &#x2013; and the the carriages in which there
               were no seats left were no better off We were directly invaded by a whole army of
               human-beings who could not even get in and who had to hold on by the sides, (or
               passerelle). Then the screaming of the people left behind and the howling and the
               cheering of the people who had places mixed in one long yell which died by degrees
               but was <del hand="hgk">always</del>
               <add hand="hgk">invariably</add> taken up again by the people in the train every time
               we went through a tunnel or passed any habitation or any living creature. In
                  <placeName key="49096">Paris</placeName> all made a rush and consequently nobody
               could move.<add hand="hgk"> and We came home very tired.</add> At <add hand="hgk">the
                  gare</add> S<hi rend="ul.2">
                  <hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> Lazare we found <persName key="904">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Scudamore</persName> who had got into carriage and not onto the Imperial.
                  <persName key="642">M<hi rend="ul.2">
                     <hi rend="sup">eurs</hi>
                  </hi> Cook</persName> and <persName key="904">Scudamore</persName> made me accept
               8.50. as giving back.<note type="com">Am Schluß dieses Eintrages ist eine Passage
                  durch zwei X markiert. Da keine Einweisungszeichen vorhanden sind, wurde die
                  Passage an der Stelle belassen. Nachträgliche Eintragungen erfolgten mit schwarzer
                  Tinte und sind so deutlich zu erkennen.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>