<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="195434">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="80179">Göteborg</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1885-05-28">28.5.1885</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>28.5.1885 Donnerstag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="80179">Gothenburg</placeName>. May 28. 1885.</p>
            <p>Started for the <placeName key="57039">Trollhätta</placeName> at 7.10 this morning.
               The whole way there thought about <persName key="75366">Kristiania</persName>. Very nice
               gentleman in carriage with us. scenery very pretty on the way (there). At Station
                  <placeName key="57039">Trollhätta</placeName> at 10. First eat some execrably bad
               ragout at <orgName key="67004">Hotel Trollhättan</orgName>, then took a little boy to lead us
               to the Cataracts. First he took us to the Locks. All one above the other. Then along
               the Göta Elfe which here winds though rocks covered with pines. Very soon we heard
               the noise of the first cataract. The whole rapids are over a mile long. The first is
               the smallest, but very fine. The boy took us to a tower from which we had a view over
               the whole rapids, then down to the old lock which is now a very pretty waterfall.
               From there to the large cataract. The Göta Elf is here about twice as broad as the
               Seine. We went over a bridge, the fall nearly deafening me, on to a little island in
               the middle of the cataracts. On both sides the water surges and boils up as if it was
               lushed by a gigantic whip. It is impossible to describe the roar with with this
               enormous mass of water bounds down over the rocks, nor the beauty of the scenery. One
               could sit there hours and look at it and always find new beauties. Especially on the
               bridges the scene is indescribably grand: the bare rocks with here and there a pine,
               rising out of the foam which splashes and bounds around them as though it would
               swallow them up in its seething bosom. After a while we went up one of the colossal
               boulders which stud the country but lost our way and had to go down and get the boy
               to lead us, This he did and we had a magnificent view of the whole falls, but not to
               be compared to the indescribably grand scene from the bridge below. From here he led
               us back to the <orgName key="67004">Hotel</orgName>, where we had some beer and coffee and
                  <persName key="856">aunt Lulu</persName> bought some Knackebrö. At 3 we got into
               the carriage and drove to the station where we had to wait some time before the train
               started. As we came into <placeName key="80179">Gothenburg</placeName> we saw a large
               fire and when we got out the whole town was running that way. The only cab in the
               place was taken away from us before our very noses by another man so that we had with
               the really dreadful shawlpacket to walk to the Uffo. The captain
               promised to wait a quarter of an hour for us. But with our general luck here again
               the one cab was taken by a family with a lot of trunks before we could get it, so
               that we again had to walk. <persName key="856">Aunt Lulu</persName> gave the
               shawlpacket a boy to carry and he of course lost her waterproof over which she
               lamented dreadfully and began to cry. We at last got a cab and drove to the
                  <orgName key="67004">Hotel</orgName> where we packed everything in a dreadful hurry, but of
               course missed the Uffo over which <persName key="856">aunt Lulu</persName>
               again began to cry. However I managed to calm her and we had dinner, an <hi rend="ul">abominable</hi> beefsteak at the <orgName key="67000">Göta Källare</orgName>. From here we
               went to the same garden we had been at the day before
               and heard the music. At 9.35 after tea and two eggs we started for <placeName key="49335">Malmö</placeName> in a very nice Coupé. I broke my stick though in
               getting into the train.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>