<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="194649">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="80179">Göteborg</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1885-05-27">27.5.1885</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">12.11.1881 &#x2013; 7.9.1887</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>27.5.1885 Mittwoch</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="80179">Gothenburg</placeName>. May 27. 1885</p>
            <p>Arrived here this morning after a dreadful passage. When I awoke I noticed the ship
               was rolling very suspiciously; but I quickly got up threw on my clothes and went on
               deck where sat down. The motion of the machine was so dreadful though that I began to
               feel very funny. So I counted everything I could, trees, windmills, mountains to keep
               my attention occupied. At last I had to rush to the side and was dreadfully sick. I
               lay down then in the cabin and was alright till <persName key="856">aunt
                  Lulu</persName> called me to tell me we were in <placeName key="80179">Göteborg</placeName>. I was then again dreadfully ill and was glad to get on land
               where we drove to the <orgName key="67000">Hotel Göta Källare</orgName> (sp. Chaéllare). It was
               the first time I set my foot on Swedish ground. Very nice
                  <orgName key="67000">hotel</orgName>. When we had washed we went down to breakfast. After
               breakfast wrote postcard, then jumped into a cab and drove as quickly as possible to
               the Station to go to the Trollhättan. Just as we came into the station the train
               whistled. I rushed onto the platform <persName key="856">aunt Lulu</persName> after
               me. I caught hold of a door and had already opened it when a most impertinent man
               caught hold of it and shut it before our very noses and the train steamed out of the
               station. <persName key="856">Aunt Lulu</persName> was dreadfully excited, began to
               cry, shrieked at me and every body else, so that It was quite fearful. At last I
               managed to quiet her and we went back to the <orgName key="67000">Hotel</orgName>. From there to
                  Photograph Shop and by tram to the <placeName key="57040">Slottkogen</placeName> a very pretty park near here. We walked in it a little and
               then went back by tram and dined middlingly at the <orgName key="67000">Hotel</orgName>. After
               dinner took a drive in a very nice little victoria. The man first drove us to a kind
               of bellevue The way went through forests and rocks. The whole country here is covered
               with colossal boulders two or three hundred feet high, with here and there a patch of
               grass or a hardy tree hanging on to it. These boulders rise abruptly out of the
               valley as if some giant had strewn them about at random. Sometimes out of fruitful
               fields, sometimes out of a forest. Some of them are smaller, some regular mountains,
               but all equally desolate and jugged and contrasting strangely with the fruitful
               fields and the green forests which grow about their base. They are not single but
               rise in regular chains from the sea on one side up to the mountain on the other; From
               one of these boulders we had the view the coachman had driven us to see, and a fine
               one indeed. On one side the sea cutting right into the land, the steep rocks falling
               into it and the little red roofed houses strewn like nests around it, on the other
               the desert and desolate mountains with hardly a tree or a bit of grass on them and
               the fruitful valleys spreading around them. From here we drove through the town,
               which is really very fine, to another point de vue. Not so fine as the first. On the
               way saw lots of children. Remarkably pretty; large blue eyes, fair hair; almost all
               go barelegged and bare footed, and it is a pleasure to see them their legs and feet
               are so well made. In fact all Swedes are more or less handsome. I have never in my
               life seen such a handsome set of people. Slim, tall, beautiful skin. One can see they
               are the descendants of the Vikings of olden days. Almost all have got remarkably
               pleasant faces. From here we drove home through the <placeName key="57040">Slottkogen</placeName>. At Home I first wrote some postcards and then went out to
               change my photographs but did not do it as the others were too large. After this we
               went to a kind of musical garden, if one can call the place so, and there eat some
               ice-kagen. From there to Lorentzberg another such kind of
               garden. After having heard some music I went in search of a nightshirt as I have
               forgotten all mine in <placeName key="49313">Copenhagen</placeName>; but all th shops
               were shut. Afterwards dined and eat some Knackebrö which is delicious at dinner. In
               the morning we also went to the <orgName key="67003">museum</orgName>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>