<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.dla-marbach.de/fileadmin/editionsprojekte/edview/EdView_Tagebuch.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--Transformiert zu EdView_Tagebuch.rng-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc n="194212">
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry Graf Kessler, Tagebuch 1880-1937</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <orgName key="71990" cert="high">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
               <persName key="71920" role="editor" cert="high">Roland S. Kamzelak</persName>
               <persName key="81247" role="editor" cert="high">Ulrich Ott</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName key="71990">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <availability>
               <ab type="editiontype">QE</ab>
               <p>Dieses Dokument ist ggf. rechtlich geschützt. Bitte informieren Sie sich in der Rubrik Rechte des Paratextes.</p>
               <ab type="Kürzel">HGKTA</ab>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <ab type="location">
               <placeName type="write" key="49084">Pyrmont</placeName>
            </ab>
            <ab type="date">
               <date when="1880-07-12">12.7.1880</date>
            </ab>
            <ab type="role">
               <persName key="8299" role="author">Harry Graf Kessler</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <institution key="71990" role="property">Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach</institution>
                     <repository/>
                     <idno>A:Kessler</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <ab type="leaves"/>
                        <ab type="pages"/>
                        <ab type="type">di</ab>
                        <ab type="subtype">or</ab>
                        <ab type="edition">Volltext</ab>
                        <ab type="scripttype"/>
                        <ab type="paper"/>
                        <ab type="physEntity">16.6.1880 &#x2013; 30.4.1881</ab>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc n="manuscript">
                        <handNote/>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <desc/>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msDesc>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>12.7.1880 Montag</head>
            <p>
               <placeName type="write" key="49084">Pyrmont</placeName> 12 July
      1880</p>
            <p>We (<persName key="176">Papa</persName> and I) visit the
      palace of the <persName key="562">princes of Waldeck</persName> this
      morning. This palace is lain
               <note type="com">Das Wort "lain" ist mit Bleistift durchgestrichen, dafür wurde "situated" gesetzt.</note>
               in the Anlagen and
    surrounded by a wide ditch We crossed the bridge and arrived at the great iron
    gate which a man opened<add hand="hgk">;</add> this man told us that
    <persName key="562">the prince of Waldeck</persName> did not live here and only very
    rarely came even in the summer, and that he had been here the last year, but
    not yet this year and that his residence was <placeName key="78754">Arolsten</placeName>. This
    palace was built in 1562 and rebuilt in 1706, it sufferd
    many sieges in the 30 years war He then took us on the walls who&#x2019;s date
    of erection one does not know but which one thinks to be very old. On these
    walls there is a beautyfull allee
               <note type="com">Kessler hat nachträglich 
      mit Bleistift zu "beautiful alley" verbessert.</note> of old trees and at
    it&#x2019;s extremity there is an old tree which is supposed to be 700 years
    old and who&#x2019;s branches are kept together with chains which are supposed
    to have been put on a hundred years ago. This tree has six meters round and its
    roots go right in to the water and have made a regular mountain of the earth.
    It&#x2019;s branches touch the ground and spring up again like new trees so
    that when you are under the tree you are in a regular little forest The man
    then shewed us the bed of <persName key="563">the count of Gleichen</persName> and
               his two wives<note type="com">Seine wirkliche Frau, <persName key="18904">Gräfin von Orlamunde</persName>, und die sarazenische <persName key="81312">Prinzessin Melechsala</persName>, die ihm das Leben gerettet haben soll.</note>, which is immensly high and big and all
    sculpted; at each corner there is a little angel looking in to it and at one of
    the ends there are three heads and two casks
               
               <note type="com">Kessler hat nachträglich 
      mit Bleistift statt "casks" das Wort "helms" gesetzt.</note>. It is all
    full of worms the wall of the room in which it is is all painted with views of
    different places and there is one <name type="work" key="36677">picture</name> by <persName key="16181">Tischbein</persName> representing <persName key="563">the Count of
    Gleichen</persName> and his two wives All the rest of the
    furniture is made of common unpealed wood like you find on the ground in the
    forest. Our man then shewed us an underground passage which is said to go right
    under the waterworks; we then returned and in the afternoon went to the
    Jägerbuche a tree somewhat like the one in the castle but only smaller.
    From this beach there is a lovely view and one is supposed to see the
    <name type="work" key="36413">Hermannsdenkmal</name>
               <note type="reg">
                  <persName key="16376">Bandel</persName>
               </note> but we did not see the least scrap of
    it</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>